<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: guides | Peter Shin]]></title>
  <link href="http://peterdotjs.github.com/blog/categories/guides/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://peterdotjs.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-21T11:16:10-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://peterdotjs.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Peter J. Shin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a Chrome Extension: Maintenance and Beyond]]></title>
    <link href="http://peterdotjs.github.com/creating-a-chrome-extension-a-developers-retrospective-part-5-maintenance-bug-fixes/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-27T10:49:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://peterdotjs.github.com/creating-a-chrome-extension-a-developers-retrospective-part-5-maintenance-bug-fixes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Updates</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="../images/extensionUpdate.png" width="400" height="400" title="Extension update" ></p>

<p>Whether it be bug fixes or enhancements you'll likely need to update your extension after the initial release. The deployment process itself is exactly the same. You'll have an additional option to deploy to a percentage of users for smoke testing. As stated before you'll just need to update the version property in the manifest to a newer one. If you're using source control make sure to tag your releases so if anything goes wrong with an update you can quickly revert back to a previous version. There will be plenty of enhancement requests that come your way once your user base grows but take all feedback with a grain of salt. If the feature enhancement doesn't make sense for your product - don't consider it. Users will ask for anything and everything but you'll have the end decision on whether to push it or not. Tab Resize has had many feature requests - some that made sense and some that didn't. The requests that did make sense have greatly improved the extension overall and it wouldn't have been possible if not for users reaching out. When used correctly, user feedback can take your app to the next level.</p>

<p>Be sure to inform users of any updates or bug fixes that you deploy. An awesome new feature that isn't discoverable is completely useless. I'd suggest adding a popup after the user opens up the updated extension so they'll know exactly what has changed. You can use localstorage to store the current version decide accordingly what to do. Through the Chrome API you can also listen to install or update event and execute callbacks as required.</p>

<h2>Monetization</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="../images/buyMeCoffee.png" title="Donations" ></p>

<p>After your user base grows you'll probably be contacted by several monetization firms asking if you would like to partner with them. It'll involve adding a snippet of JavaScript to your extension where you'll get a certain amount of money based on the number of active users per time period. I'm not against monetization but personally I found it a risk that I didn't want to take. The monetization sounded very tempting but I didn't want to take the chance of it affecting the user experience or Google's terms and conditions. Google has strict policies on the way ads are injected so you'll want to be careful. The firms that had reached out in the past has promised that the user experience wouldn't be affected but I didn't think it was worth the risk. You can also try adding a donate or buy me a coffee button but from what I've read those <a href="http://bloggerabroad.com/donate-button-blog" title="Why a Donate Button Will Hurt Your Blog">aren't very successful</a>. Personally, I didn't want to build something that was "free" with strings attached. Unless you are trying to offset server or API costs, just think of it as paying it forward with your code.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a Chrome Extension: Production]]></title>
    <link href="http://peterdotjs.github.com/creating-a-chrome-extension-a-developers-retrospective-part-4-production/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-25T17:27:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://peterdotjs.github.com/creating-a-chrome-extension-a-developers-retrospective-part-4-production</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Deployment</h2>

<p>Google has provided very clear <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/webstore/publish" title="documentation">documentation</a> on how to publish your app. Here are a couple tips on the process:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Upload</strong>: Whenever you update a package you'll need to update the version number in the manifest - it'll be blocked otherwise.</li>
<li><strong>Description</strong>: Add search keywords/tags in your description. It'll help your ranking when users search for those terms in the web store. This will be a good place to add your source control link so users can add issues or look at the source code. Here you can notify the users if you are sending any anonymous tracking information. Also this would be good place to address any of the permissions that you have required and why you need then.</li>
<li><strong>Promotional Images</strong>: Make sure to fill out all the promotional images so you can maximize your impression count.</li>
<li><strong>Websites</strong>: Add a website if you have one. This adds credibility and confidence to the extension.</li>
<li><strong>Category</strong>: When choosing a category, you may want to choose one they has fewer applications. Many extensions fall under productivity (as extensions by nature were designed to make us more productive) but it likely will get lost in the numerous other extensions out there already.</li>
<li><strong>Screenshots</strong>: Utilize all the 5 spots you have for screenshots. What you'll find is that users will likelihood never read your description. With the limited amount of time you have to describe what you app can/cant do I think having a video is the best and quickest way to deliver this information. If you don't want to go to the trouble, make sure to have great screen shots that showcase your app.</li>
<li><strong>Language</strong>: For now choose the language you've build your extension in. After you get some more data from Google Analytics you may decide it would be worth supporting l10n of other languages.</li>
<li><strong>Analytics</strong>: Create a Google Analytics account if you haven't already fill out the Google Analytics ID.</li>
</ol>


<h2>User Feedback</h2>

<p>The one grief I have with the Chrome web store is the current user feedback system. The current system is fairly one sided. If a user leaves a review the developer cannot address it directly. Only if a user leaves feedback in the "support" tab are you able to directly reply. But even then there is no notification system. You can reply to this specific feedback but there isn't a way to confirm if the original poster even sees your reply. If you end up receiving some bad reviews it's kind of like getting punched with your hands tied. You won't be able to defend yourself and you can't do much about it.</p>

<p>With both good and bad reviews the overall feedback is invaluable. While some feedback may be repetitive and not particularly helpful, it's something that you must pay attention to if you want your extension to be successful. The user feedback will give you hints to any underlying issues or bugs as well as features you are missing and can improve. If you've never gotten public feedback on an application you've built then you're in for a treat. The public can be incredibly nice and generous, but they can be just as harsh and negative. It's hard not to take it personally the first time but you'll get used it it, kind of. I remember the first time I received a bad review on Tab Resize, I was totally crushed. And it is hard to to be. Most extensions are built by developers in their free time. It's their passion and it's very personal. But after a while you'll get used to it, taking the bad with the good. For me, I look at the positive reviews as fuel to get over the not so great reviews.</p>

<p>Lack of empathy I think is the cause of most of these bad reviews. Louis C.K. shares my opinion.</p>

<iframe width="853" height="480" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/5HbYScltf1c?" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p> Many individuals are unable to see that there is someone behind the scenes. Someone who spent time building a free app for everyone to use, only to get berated for it. Developers would be hard-pressed to give an extension a 1 star review as they know of the amount of effort that actually goes in.</p>

<p>Some Tab Resize verbatims from our 1 star reviewers who failed to understand the purpose of the extension:</p>

<ul>
<li>"This add-on is a useless piece of crap."</li>
<li>"Broken failed plugin."</li>
<li>"It works terribly."</li>
<li>"doesn t works waste of time"</li>
<li>"Sorry to say but this is a rather lousy and really unnecessary add on."</li>
</ul>


<p>Regardless of what you put in your description, screenshot or video, many users will just look at an extension name and instantly have certain and specific expectations. Once they start using it, if those expectations aren't met, they won't be shy in letting you know how wrong you are.</p>

<p>On the other hand here are some verbatims from their happier 5 star counterparts:</p>

<ul>
<li>"Works as expected and has a simple, clean menu. Now has multi-monitor support and feeds my cat."</li>
<li>"Super useful tool that has increased my productivity. Thank you!"</li>
<li>"I love it just what I need it thank you."</li>
<li>"GREAT!"</li>
<li>"love it!!!!"</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Haters are always going to hate. Work on your app for those that appreciate it and don't worry about everyone else.</strong></p>

<h2>Press</h2>

<p>By informing tech blogs of your extension you'll have the best chance of getting the word out immediately. While this may increase the exposure and the number of visits it may have some consequences. If the features aren't yet mature and rich enough it may get panned and end up greatly hurting your average rating. On the other hand if it takes off you can try to ride that viral wave for as long as possible. When I released Tab Resize more than 2 years ago, I never even thought about this. I had just deployed it and shared it with some friends. It grew organically and slowly at a steady rate until a year later the right person blogged about it and some more well known blogs took notice, specifically <a href="http://www.cnet.com/how-to/split-chrome-tabs-into-multiwindow-preset-layouts-with-tab-resize" title="CNET - tab resize">CNET</a> and <a href="http://lifehacker.com/tab-resize-automatically-organizes-tabs-into-preset-lay-1306865451" title="Lifehacker - tab resize">Lifehacker</a>.</p>

<p><img src="../images/chromeStoreSessions.png" title="Chrome Store Sessions" ></p>

<p>The peak in visits were a result of certain blog posts. More Visits -> More Installs -> More Users. But take note that more users means more ratings which may not be a good thing. I think during this period of time Tab Resize's rating went down from a high 4 to a low 3. Pay close attention to the feedback you get around this time as you might need or want to deploy features/fixes quickly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a Chrome Extension: Testing]]></title>
    <link href="http://peterdotjs.github.com/creating-a-chrome-extension-a-developers-retrospective-part-3-testing/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-24T16:44:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://peterdotjs.github.com/creating-a-chrome-extension-a-developers-retrospective-part-3-testing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Cross Platform</h2>

<p>The great part of building a browser specific extension is you'll only need to test for that browser. With Chrome for the most part you'll only need to support the latest browser depending on the APIs that you're planning to use. If you are using a relatively new API you can either perform some feature checking in your code or you can add some version requirements to your manifest.</p>

<p>Even though you'll get by not testing other browsers, you should do some checks across different operating systems. Depending on your application it may attract more users of one OS versus another - Tab Resize had the following distribution  in the past 5 months:</p>

<p><img src="../images/deviceDistr.png" title="Device Distribution" ></p>

<p>Once you get some data you'll be able to determine the tier 1 and 2 platforms to test on.</p>

<p>Although all the APIs should behave the same way, I've actually found a couple that act different in certain platforms. Differently may mean it still works or it may mean the API itself is completely broken.</p>

<p>If you do find an issue with one of the Chrome APIs you can <a href="https://code.google.com/p/chromium/issues/list" title="issues list">file a bug</a> or in all likelyhood search find an existing issue that's similar your own.</p>

<p>As with everything else in life try to have unit and integration tests so regression bugs won't pop up. And also be sure to test how upgrades interact with the prevsious version (especially if you are persisting any data or preferences). Users can always remove and reinstall but this adds to a poor user experience.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a Chrome Extension: Development]]></title>
    <link href="http://peterdotjs.github.com/creating-a-chrome-extension-a-developers-retrospective-part-2-development/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-24T00:25:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://peterdotjs.github.com/creating-a-chrome-extension-a-developers-retrospective-part-2-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Intro</h2>

<p>As there are plenty of existing tutorials on how to get started on developing a Chrome extension, I will only cover a few topics and specific things to look out for.</p>

<h2>APIs</h2>

<p>Chrome provides really great documentation on their available  <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/extensions/api_index" title="JavaScript APIs">JavaScript APIs</a>. Depending on your use case some functionality may or may not be exposed to the user. There are stable, beta, dev, and experimental APIs to use. You're choice of APIs will greatly depend on the type of extension you are trying to build as well as your audience. As an example the following Chrome APIs were used for Tab resize.</p>

<ul>
<li>chrome.browserAction - setting badge text/background</li>
<li>chrome.windows - create, update, getting current window</li>
<li>chrome.tabs - create, move, get, query tab information</li>
<li>chrome.commands - keyboard shortcuts</li>
<li>chrome.system - display monitor info</li>
<li>chrome.extension - get background page</li>
<li>chrome.runtime - send messages between background page and popup</li>
</ul>


<h2>Manifest</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/extensions/manifest" title="Manifest">manifest</a> is a JSON structure to describe your extension project. The version, description, icons, and shortcut commands are just a few of the many different fields that can be set in the manifest.</p>

<p>One of the most important fields is the "permissions" property. You'll want to think through your project and ensure that you know of all the APIs you will need now and in the near future so you can properly request for permission ahead of time. The caveat with permissions is that if you want to add a new permission after you've deployed - it's a generally poor experience to users that have already installed your extension. When their extension is updated with a newly required permission, the extension automatically gets disabled and the user will be prompted. This isn't an approach you would want to take when you have a large user base. Another approach is to use the "optional_permissions" field so that the extension does not automatically get disabled. All users will get prompted of the optional permissions that are required. In either case you may end up giving a subpar user experience to a good number of your users.</p>

<p>Just try your best to get all the permissions you need ahead of time so it'll be a much smoother process later down the line.</p>

<h2>Tracking</h2>

<p>If you care about improving your app and growing it, tracking is needed without question. User feedback can only go so far. Analytical tracking data will tell you what your users actually do and you can improve/change things accordingly.</p>

<p>As an example I found that a user was actually creating a custom resize layout with of 99x99. When the user clicks on this custom created layout 9801 windows would have been created on their desktop, definitely crashing Chrome and probably their computer along the way. Benefiting from this info, I added some enforcement to limit the input size. Sometimes you need to protect the users from themselves, especially if they aren't using the application as intended.</p>

<p>When you setup the extension in the web store, make sure to put a Google Analytics id number - this will track the users that hit the Chrome web store page of your extension. It'll be really usefully to see the trend of your views as well as where the referrals are coming from.</p>

<p>I used Google Analytics for tracking but obviously you aren't limited to it. Regarding Google Analytics - the <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/extensions/tut_analytics" title="tracking documentation">tracking documentation</a> as of this writing for Chrome extensions is out of date. If you choose to use Google Analytics you should start using the <a href="https://developers.google.com/analytics/devguides/collection/analyticsjs/" title="universal analytics">universal analytics</a> framework instead.</p>

<p>Personally, I've found it really interesting to see how Tab Resize grew over time and how it was being used in countries I've never even heard of. If you do decide to use tracking <strong>be sure to add in an option for users to opt out of participating</strong>. This is a better user experience and also required by Google's terms and agreement.</p>

<h2>Usability</h2>

<p>Using the results of your tracking you'll be able to see if users are actually using the app as you intended. The data will tell you a story of how people are using it, either it be in a way you intended or in a way you never even thought of. Armed with this information you'll be able to iterate on and improve your app. Features that aren't being used as frequently can be shown more prominently and features that aren't being used at all should be considered for the chopping block. None of this should be news to you but I hope you can push your users to use the product as you imagined rather than just the other way around.</p>

<h2>Artwork</h2>

<p>Artwork will influence both usability and impression rate. You'll need artwork for icons, sprites, as well as logo designs. They have some <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/webstore/images" title="images">requirements</a> for these images. You'll definitely want to look them over otherwise your extension may be rejected. You want to at least to have a 440x280 promotional image. Without this size, your extension will be pushed to the bottom of the list when extensions are surfaced in the store.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="../images/440x280v3.png" title="My attempt at promo design" ></p>

<p>While many developers may easily look over visual design, it's a really important piece that you simply cannot ignore, especially in this day and age. Users have grown accustomed to smooth and sleek designs and expect nothing less. If you had two apps with similar functionality, the one with a better user interface will definitely win out. If you don't have experience with a graphics editor and don't have an interest in learning there are still other options. From <a href="http://99designs.com" title="99designs">99designs</a> to <a href="https://www.fiverr.com" title="fiverr">fieverr</a> there are many ways for you get great artwork without being an artist yourself. There really isn't any excuse for having a bad design.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a Chrome Extension: Inception]]></title>
    <link href="http://peterdotjs.github.com/creating-a-chrome-extension-a-developers-retrospective-part-1-inception/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-07T18:19:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://peterdotjs.github.com/creating-a-chrome-extension-a-developers-retrospective-part-1-inception</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>The idea</h2>

<p>You should definitely read Paul Graham's article on <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/startupideas.html" title="start up ideas">startup ideas</a> if you haven't yet already. Most products come out of an  existing problem. This problem may be unoticed, compensated for or perhaps very difficult to solve. Workarounds exist everywhere in our daily lives and if you could find one to make more efficient then you likely have a product on your hands.</p>

<p>Assuming you've brain stormed several ideas, now it's time to face the music and search for similar solutions. Although it might be hearbreaking to find that someone else had come up with that same awesome idea that you had - it's not at all the end of the world. In fact it might even help you. If you research your competitors you can find all their pain points, user feedback, and areas where you can improve upon. I've seen many extensions that were great ideas to begin with but simply weren't executed well. Either it be the user experience, the design or bugs in the product, these are all areas where you could improve upon. However, if there are already several great and solid products out there you should probably consider contributing to one of them rather than creating your own. The world may not need another adblock tool or responsive web tester.</p>

<h3>[Tab Resize]</h3>

<p>I found myself manually resizing windows across my monitor and realized just how inefficient that workflow was. I compensated by doing it by hand but I figured that there had to be some kind of extension to do this for me. I did a search on the Chrome Web store and found several that were in the ballpark of what I was looking for ("Split Screen", "Tab Scissors", "Dualless", etc.) These extensions each do something different but each had their own respective limitations. Once I realized that there was room in the market for a split screen layout extension, I knew it was worth building. At this point the idea of having users didn't cross my mind.  I figured at the very least I'd be able to use it and make my own life a little easier.</p>

<h2>Requirements and Design</h2>

<p>In both school and in industry there is somone telling you what do to; a professor and program manager respectively that will describe in detail the requirements of the project that you are venturing on. In addition, the design (both technology and visual) are also determined for you (usually). With a project that is completely of your own, you may find youself overwhelmed with the amount of freedom and number of choice you now have. Requirements can be shaped by the problem you want to solve in addition to the areas that your competitors are lacking in. Choosing a visual design and color scheme is kind of like choosing a parking spot in a very sparse parking lot - you'll have a lot of choices and it might take some time to decide which one to use.</p>

<p>Try to pay as much attention to the user experience if not more than the actual features. Having amazing features that are difficult to use or discover will produce poor results. It goes without saying that the features the application is providing must be flawless or close to being bug free. However great the visual user experience is, it can never compensate for poor execution in function.</p>

<h3>[Tab Resize]</h3>

<h4>Requirements*:</h4>

<ol>
<li>Resize tabs into fixed layouts based on avaialble screen size</li>
<li>Current tab and tabs to the right will be considered in the resize</li>
<li>Custom layouts can be created, and existing layouts can be removed.</li>
<li>Layouts can be reset to default layouts</li>
<li>Ability to undo the previous resize</li>
<li>User preference of layouts should be saved</li>
<li>Single tab ability to only resize the current window</li>
</ol>


<h4>Design*:</h4>

<p><img src="../images/oldtabresize.png" title="Tab Resize 1.0 version from late 2012" ></p>

<p>Personally, I think choosing on the visual design itself took much longer than the actual app development. Visually I wanted a large action area where the user could easily choose the layout they wanted and easily discover the features (created, removing, and reseting layouts).  The most frequently used layout should be the easiest to get to - in this case right aligned and closest to the extension icon. Each of the features should be easy to get to. The options can be changed directly in the popup menu - not hidden in another view like an options page.</p>

<p>*The above design and requirements are from the first version that was deployed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
